<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-08T19:53:46+11:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ClimateExplorer</title><subtitle>The official blog of https://climateexplorer.net.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">To simplify and consolidate</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/10/08/to-simplify-and-consolidate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To simplify and consolidate" /><published>2024-10-08T19:50:00+11:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T19:50:00+11:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/10/08/to-simplify-and-consolidate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/10/08/to-simplify-and-consolidate.html">&lt;p&gt;Until recently, ClimateExplorer was sourcing temperature and precipitation data for locations from multiple sources. We started ClimateExplorer by using data from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/&quot;&gt;Australian Climate Observations Reference Network – Surface Air Temperature (ACORN-SAT)&lt;/a&gt;. It expanded to include &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/current/annual/ria/summary.shtml&quot;&gt;Remote Islands and Antarctica&lt;/a&gt; and to New Zealand’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://niwa.co.nz/climate-and-weather/nz-temperature-record/seven-station-series-temperature-data&quot;&gt;7-station series&lt;/a&gt; and 11-station series from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://niwa.co.nz/&quot;&gt;National Institute of Water and Atmospheric Research (NIWA)&lt;/a&gt;. Adding these locations, one country at a time, didn’t seem like a very scalable approach, but I was yet to find a suitable collated global dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/datasets/2024/06/02/the-rest-of-the-world.html&quot;&gt;Global Historical Climatology Network&lt;/a&gt; is part of ClimateExplorer, it made sense to standardise how ClimateExplorer worked for every location. To that end, the website now only has 3 datasets. They are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GHCN: monthly mean temperature and precipitation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ACORN-SAT: daily mean temperature and precipitation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadcet/&quot;&gt;HadCET&lt;/a&gt;/HadCEP: daily mean temperature and precipitation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change has made mean temperature the default temperature data. Maximum and minimum temperatures are still available for every site (via GHCNd for most sites), but the presets will give you mean temperature (it used to be either maximum or mean temperature, depending on the dataset).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All sites now have adjusted and unadjusted temperature records and, if available, precipitation data. If we’d kept RAIA and NIWA datasets there would have been weird inconsistencies in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="datasets" /><summary type="html">Until recently, ClimateExplorer was sourcing temperature and precipitation data for locations from multiple sources. We started ClimateExplorer by using data from Australian Climate Observations Reference Network – Surface Air Temperature (ACORN-SAT). It expanded to include Remote Islands and Antarctica and to New Zealand’s 7-station series and 11-station series from the National Institute of Water and Atmospheric Research (NIWA). Adding these locations, one country at a time, didn’t seem like a very scalable approach, but I was yet to find a suitable collated global dataset.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Global Historical Climatology Network daily</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/09/21/GHCN-daily.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Global Historical Climatology Network daily" /><published>2024-09-21T21:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-09-21T21:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/09/21/GHCN-daily</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/09/21/GHCN-daily.html">&lt;p&gt;After we added &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/datasets/2024/06/02/the-rest-of-the-world.html&quot;&gt;The rest of the world&lt;/a&gt; (i.e., adding sites from around the world, sourced from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/products/land-based-station/global-historical-climatology-network-monthly&quot;&gt;Global Historical Climatology Network monthly (GHCNm)&lt;/a&gt;), I thought it would be worthwhile to acquire the daily data for those sites from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/products/land-based-station/global-historical-climatology-network-daily&quot;&gt;Global Historical Climatology Network daily (GHCNd)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, this seemed like a daunting task. We had selected 1883 sites from GHCNm. GHCNd data files for those sites total over 7 gigabytes. I wanted it to be a few hundred megabytes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do would be to transform the GHCNd file into something that &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/&quot;&gt;Climate Explorer&lt;/a&gt; could use. The data file format in GHCNd looks like the below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;STATION&quot;,&quot;DATE&quot;,&quot;LATITUDE&quot;,&quot;LONGITUDE&quot;,&quot;ELEVATION&quot;,&quot;NAME&quot;,&quot;PRCP&quot;,&quot;PRCP_ATTRIBUTES&quot;,&quot;SNWD&quot;,&quot;SNWD_ATTRIBUTES&quot;,&quot;TMAX&quot;,&quot;TMAX_ATTRIBUTES&quot;,&quot;TMIN&quot;,&quot;TMIN_ATTRIBUTES&quot;,&quot;TAVG&quot;,&quot;TAVG_ATTRIBUTES&quot;
&quot;AG000060590&quot;,&quot;1892-01-01&quot;,&quot;30.5667&quot;,&quot;2.8667&quot;,&quot;397.0&quot;,&quot;EL GOLEA, AG&quot;,&quot;    0&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,,,,&quot;   34&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,
&quot;AG000060590&quot;,&quot;1892-01-02&quot;,&quot;30.5667&quot;,&quot;2.8667&quot;,&quot;397.0&quot;,&quot;EL GOLEA, AG&quot;,&quot;    0&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,,,,&quot;   36&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,
&quot;AG000060590&quot;,&quot;1892-01-03&quot;,&quot;30.5667&quot;,&quot;2.8667&quot;,&quot;397.0&quot;,&quot;EL GOLEA, AG&quot;,&quot;    0&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,,,,&quot;   30&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,
&quot;AG000060590&quot;,&quot;1892-01-04&quot;,&quot;30.5667&quot;,&quot;2.8667&quot;,&quot;397.0&quot;,&quot;EL GOLEA, AG&quot;,&quot;    0&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,,,,&quot;   40&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,
&quot;AG000060590&quot;,&quot;1892-01-05&quot;,&quot;30.5667&quot;,&quot;2.8667&quot;,&quot;397.0&quot;,&quot;EL GOLEA, AG&quot;,&quot;    0&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,,,,&quot;   30&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,
&quot;AG000060590&quot;,&quot;1892-01-06&quot;,&quot;30.5667&quot;,&quot;2.8667&quot;,&quot;397.0&quot;,&quot;EL GOLEA, AG&quot;,&quot;    0&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,,,,&quot;   24&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,
&quot;AG000060590&quot;,&quot;1892-01-07&quot;,&quot;30.5667&quot;,&quot;2.8667&quot;,&quot;397.0&quot;,&quot;EL GOLEA, AG&quot;,&quot;    0&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,,,,&quot;   38&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,
&quot;AG000060590&quot;,&quot;1892-01-08&quot;,&quot;30.5667&quot;,&quot;2.8667&quot;,&quot;397.0&quot;,&quot;EL GOLEA, AG&quot;,&quot;    0&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,,,,&quot;   84&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,
&quot;AG000060590&quot;,&quot;1892-01-09&quot;,&quot;30.5667&quot;,&quot;2.8667&quot;,&quot;397.0&quot;,&quot;EL GOLEA, AG&quot;,&quot;    0&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,,,,&quot;   40&quot;,&quot;,,E&quot;,,
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClimateExplorer will only use max/min temperature and precipitation from GHCNd. However, we found that precipitation and temperature data are not correlated. A site may have records for one and not the other. It makes sense to separate the two types of data into different files. We transformed the file above into a temperature file…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Date,TMax,TMin
19400101,202,44
19400102,212,62
19400103,232,70
19400104,231,106
19400105,202,80
19400106,198,65
19400107,218,72
19400108,222,70
19400109,213,76
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and a precipitation file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Date,Precipitation
18920101,0
18920102,0
18920103,0
18920104,0
18920105,0
18920106,0
18920107,0
18920108,0
18920109,0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a check to simply discard a row (i.e., a day of data) if all of the measurements are not present. There is also a filter to discard a site if it doesn’t have at least 10 years of data with over 300 days of data for each of those years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for downloading and reducing the data to be suitable for ClimateExplorer is at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ledpup/ClimateExplorer/tree/master/ClimateExplorer.Data.Ghcnd&quot;&gt;ClimateExplorer.Data.Ghcnd&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="datasets" /><summary type="html">After we added The rest of the world (i.e., adding sites from around the world, sourced from Global Historical Climatology Network monthly (GHCNm)), I thought it would be worthwhile to acquire the daily data for those sites from the Global Historical Climatology Network daily (GHCNd).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ACORN-SAT version 2.5</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/09/03/ACORN-SAT-2.5.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACORN-SAT version 2.5" /><published>2024-09-03T20:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-09-03T20:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/09/03/ACORN-SAT-2.5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/09/03/ACORN-SAT-2.5.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/&quot;&gt;ACORN-SAT&lt;/a&gt; 2.5 was released in August 2024. This release includes temperature data until the end of 2023. ClimateExplorer has been updated to this dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/&quot;&gt;Bureau of Meteorology&lt;/a&gt; (BoM) made the following statement concerning version 2.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;ACORN-SAT 2.5 includes new or reassessed adjustments at 15 of the 112 ACORN-SAT locations. Previously applied adjustments at 5 locations were removed after being found to be no longer significant with the inclusion of additional data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Analysis has shown the changed adjustments in ACORN-SAT 2.5 have had a negligible impact on estimated long-term warming trend in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Full details of all adjustments, including the time periods and reference periods used, are available in the station catalogue. The Bureau’s ACORN-SAT dataset and methods have been thoroughly peer-reviewed and found to be world-leading. Further information on the dataset and the reasons for adjustments can be found in the ACORN-SAT &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/#tabs=FAQs&quot;&gt;FAQ section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications-of-using-acorn-sat-in-climateexplorer&quot;&gt;Implications of using ACORN-SAT in ClimateExplorer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside of using ACORN-SAT is the 6-11 month lag in updates of the previous year. All other datasets in ClimateExplorer update the previous year’s data sometime in January of the current year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-future-improvement&quot;&gt;A future improvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculate the transfer functions that are likely to be applied (presuming no changes to the adjustment methods) and project them to the current, unadjusted data. When the latest ACORN-SAT becomes available later in the year, replace the extrapolated data with the official ACORN-SAT data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only 15 of the 112 locations in version 2.5 had any changes in the functions compared with 2.4; therefore all other locations’ adjustments to temperature applied in the same way as the previous year, resulting in the same adjusted temperatures between extrapolated and official. Of the 15 that were altered, the difference between extrapolated and official would be minimal (i.e., “a negligible impact”).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="datasets" /><summary type="html">ACORN-SAT 2.5 was released in August 2024. This release includes temperature data until the end of 2023. ClimateExplorer has been updated to this dataset.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The rest of the world</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/06/02/the-rest-of-the-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The rest of the world" /><published>2024-06-02T12:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2024-06-02T12:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/06/02/the-rest-of-the-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2024/06/02/the-rest-of-the-world.html">&lt;p&gt;In 2023 &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/&quot;&gt;Climate Explorer&lt;/a&gt; had temperature records for Australia, New Zealand and the UK. We wanted to add temperature records from all around the world. Finding a dataset that fitted our requirements wasn’t easy. Below are the required criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A dataset that has unadjusted (what was recorded on the gauge) and adjusted records (corrections due to changes at the site and fixes for errors).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the best quality and longest running stations, from the tens of thousands of available sites around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A fine-grain resolution to support the different graphs in ClimateExplorer. ClimateExplorer was built with daily minimum and maximum records in mind. ClimateExplorer doesn’t work with a higher resolution than daily records. Only since the advent of digital recording (around the 1970s and 1980s) has hourly or more frequently recorded temperatures been available and we wanted data that was longer-term. ClimateExplorer can also work with monthly and yearly records.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data from really existing stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Precipitation data for the selected stations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;initial-investigation&quot;&gt;Initial investigation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of starting with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/&quot;&gt;ACORN-SAT&lt;/a&gt; was that these criteria were easy to meet because; 1) ACORN-SAT is an adjusted data-set and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/&quot;&gt;Bureau of Meteorology&lt;/a&gt; make the unadjusted data publicly available via their website. 2) ACORN-SAT is a 112 station subset of Australia’s stations, already selected for quality and longevity. 3) ACORN-SAT is a daily dataset of maximum and minimum temperatures. 4) It’s from known stations. 5) We were able to find the precipitation data from the BoM and link it to the ACORN-SAT temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/&quot;&gt;NCEI&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.noaa.gov/&quot;&gt;NOAA&lt;/a&gt; have a few products that looked suitable. They are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/products/land-based-station/integrated-surface-database&quot;&gt;Global Hourly - Integrated Surface Database (ISD)&lt;/a&gt; - this seemed ideal at first because it has hourly data as well as a daily summary of temperature with many other data types. We could pre-process hourly records into daily records and then build in functionality to support other types of data (e.g., windspeed).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/products/land-based-station/global-historical-climatology-network-daily&quot;&gt;Global Historical Climatology Network daily (GHCNd)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/products/land-based-station/global-historical-climatology-network-monthly&quot;&gt;Global Historical Climatology Network monthly (GHCNm)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We assessed each product with the criteria specified above, at the start of this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;criterion-1---adjusted-and-raw-datasets&quot;&gt;Criterion 1 - adjusted and raw datasets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started by looking at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/products/land-based-station/integrated-surface-database&quot;&gt;ISD&lt;/a&gt;. The ISD doesn’t have an adjusted dataset. Maybe that was okay if the other criteria were met. The nice thing about ISD is that it records, as meta-data, when the station started operating and when it shutdown (if it has). The downside, however, is that it wasn’t until we started downloading all of the climate data (many gigabytes) that we saw how much of it was missing for some stations. It’s a challenge to describe a station as “good” when, although it’s been running for one hundred years, it’s missing decades of data during that time. Frustrated, we put on hold integrating ISD into ClimateExplorer and further explored what datasets were available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GHCNd was looked at next. GHCNd is also solely an unadjusted dataset. From the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/products/land-based-station/global-historical-climatology-network-daily#tab-298&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unlike GHCNm, GHCNd does not contain adjustments for biases resulting from historical changes in instrumentation and observing practices. It should be noted that historically (and in general), the deployed stations providing daily summaries for the dataset were not designed to meet all of the desired standards for climate monitoring. Rather, the deployment of the stations was to meet the demands of agriculture, hydrology, weather forecasting, aviation, etc. Because GHCNd has not been homogenized to account for artifacts associated with the various eras in reporting practice at any particular station (i.e., for changes in systematic bias), users should consider whether or not the potential for changes in systematic bias might be important to their application. In addition, GHCNd and GHCNm are not internally consistent (i.e., GHCNm is not necessarily derived from the data in GHCNd) until the release of GHCNm version 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the three NOAA products, GHCNm is the only one that meets criterion 1. NOAA explain the issue and the adjustment process as well as publishing the unadjusted data along with the adjusted data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Nearly all weather stations undergo changes to data measurement processes and infrastructure at some point in their history. Thermometers, for example, require periodic replacement or recalibration, and measurement technology has evolved over time. Temperature recording protocols have also changed at many locations from recording temperatures at fixed hours during the day to once-per-day readings of the 24-hour maximum and minimum. “Fixed” land stations are sometimes relocated, and even minor temperature equipment moves can change the microclimate exposure of the instruments. In other cases, the land use or land cover in the vicinity of an observing site can change over time, which can impact the local environment that instruments are sampling even when measurement practice is stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All of these modifications can cause systematic shifts in temperature readings that are unrelated to any real variation in local weather and climate. These shifts (or “inhomogeneities”) can be large relative to true climate variability, and can cause large systematic errors when calculating climate trends and variability for a single station as well as for the average of multiple stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For this reason, detecting and accounting for artifacts associated with changes in observing practice is an important and necessary part of building climate datasets. In GHCNm v4, shifts in monthly temperature series are detected through automated pairwise comparisons of the station series using the algorithm described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/clim/22/7/2008jcli2263.1.xml&quot;&gt;Menne and Williams (2009)&lt;/a&gt;. This procedure, known as the Pairwise Homogenization Algorithm (PHA), systematically evaluates each time series of monthly average surface air temperature to identify cases with abrupt shifts in one station’s temperature series (the “target” series) relative to many other correlated series from other stations in the region (the “reference” series). The algorithm seeks to resolve the timing of shifts for all station series before computing an adjustment factor to compensate for any one particular shift. These adjustment factors are based on the average change in the magnitude of monthly temperature differences between the target station series with the apparent shift and the reference series with no apparent concurrent shifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three versions of GHCNm. They are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;QCU: Quality Control, Unadjusted&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;QCF: Quality Control, Adjusted, using the Pairwise Homogeneity Algorithm (PHA, Menne and Williams, 2009).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;QFE: Quality Control, Adjusted, Estimated using the Pairwise Homogeneity Algorithm. Only the years 1961-2010 are provided. This is to help maximize station coverage when calculating normals. For more information, see Williams et al, 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClimateExplorer would use QCU and QCF. ClimateExplorer does not need QFE because we would calculate our own normals, from the selected stations in the process discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;criterion-2---quality-over-quantity&quot;&gt;Criterion 2 - quality over quantity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three NOAA products have different sets of stations; GHCNm has about 28,000, GHCNd has about 120,000 and ISD has about 30,000 stations. All of these datasets would break ClimateExplorer if we didn’t add in extra controls over the display of data. Trying to display 30,000 stations on the map would break it. On lists of stations, we would have to prompt the user to filter the data or partially load the data in at a few hundred records at a time. However, the main problem isn’t technological. 30,000 stations is too many for humans to make sense of. We wanted users to look at their country and see no more than hundreds of stations for their region. We wanted them to think “ClimateExplorer doesn’t have my hometown but at least they have a nearby city. That’s acceptable.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the reasons stated above, no matter which dataset we decided upon, we would want to reduce the set of stations from tens of thousands to thousands. Therefore, we needed to try to group stations geographically and then select a station from the geographical group that had the best data. A quick search online about spatial grouping, came up with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-means_clustering&quot;&gt;k-means clustering&lt;/a&gt;, so we started there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;k-means-clustering-algorithm&quot;&gt;K-Means Clustering algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia explains &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-means_clustering&quot;&gt;k-means clustering&lt;/a&gt; as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a method of vector quantization, originally from signal processing, that aims to partition &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; observations into &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; clusters in which each observation belongs to the cluster with the nearest mean (cluster centers or cluster centroid), serving as a prototype of the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above description seemed close to what we wanted. The &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; would be the number of stations in the cluster, and &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; could be how many clusters we’d end up with (wanting about 2,000) from which we could then select our best stations from within each cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/assets/k-means-clustering-algorithm.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of k-means&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A question we had was: could k-means deal with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geodetic_coordinates&quot;&gt;geodetic coordinates&lt;/a&gt; (i.e., longitude and latitude). A &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/24762435/clustering-geo-location-coordinates-lat-long-pairs-using-kmeans-algorithm-with&quot;&gt;stack-overflow question&lt;/a&gt; queried the issue; i.e., since k-means only uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclidean_distance&quot;&gt;Euclidean distance&lt;/a&gt;, would it work for places on the Earth - where we use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haversine_formula&quot;&gt;haversine formula&lt;/a&gt; to resolve the distances between locations with coordinates in latitude and longitude? The answer on stack-overlow was: “no, k-means will not work, use &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DBSCAN&quot;&gt;density-based spatial clustering of applications with noise (DBSCAN)&lt;/a&gt; with the Haversine formula to calculate distance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dbscan&quot;&gt;DBSCAN&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia explains &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DBSCAN&quot;&gt;density-based spatial clustering of applications with noise (DBSCAN)&lt;/a&gt; as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a density-based clustering non-parametric algorithm: given a set of points in some space, it groups together points that are closely packed (points with many nearby neighbors), and marks as outliers points that lie alone in low-density regions (those whose nearest neighbors are too far away). DBSCAN is one of the most common, and most commonly cited, clustering algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That description also seemed like what we wanted (in the same way that k-means appeared appropriate). We also watched some videos about DBSCAN, such as: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RDZUdRSDOok&quot;&gt;Clustering with DBSCAN, Clearly Explained!!!&lt;/a&gt; and read more on it; such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://geoffboeing.com/2014/08/clustering-to-reduce-spatial-data-set-size/&quot;&gt;Clustering to Reduce Spatial Data Set Size&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/assets/DBSCAN-density-data.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example results of DBSCAN&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did not take too much longer to find &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/viceroypenguin/Dbscan&quot;&gt;a software package for DBSCAN implemented in .NET&lt;/a&gt;. The library did not provide a haversine formula for distances, but &lt;strong&gt;did&lt;/strong&gt; provide an interface (ISpatialIndex&lt;T&gt;), enabling us to implement our own distance function to be used by the algorithm. Things were looking promising!&lt;/T&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read the section on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DBSCAN#Parameter_estimation&quot;&gt;parameter estimation&lt;/a&gt;, DBSCAN requires three parameters. They are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimum number of points in a cluster (minPts). We wanted this to be low, only 3-5 as our use of the clustering was to prune out the lower quality stations in a region and end up with only one station in the cluster. We did not want clusters as the final product.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An epsilon (ε) value. In our case this would be the maximum distance, in kilometres, between stations to still qualify as being in the same cluster. Initially, we didn’t really know what this value would be but thought that 100km seemed about right.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The distance function. We had this figured out already because we knew we wanted to use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haversine_formula&quot;&gt;haversine formula&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After running the algorithm about 20 times, a minPts of 2 and ε of 75km (then selecting the best station from each cluster) resulted in a good distribution of stations around the globe. The problem with minPts of 2 is that some papers (and Wikipedia) suggest that this is not a valid value for minPts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The low value of &lt;em&gt;minPts&lt;/em&gt; = 1 does not make sense, as then every point is a core point by definition. With &lt;em&gt;minPts&lt;/em&gt; ≤ 2, the result will be the same as of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hierarchical_clustering&quot;&gt;hierarchical clustering&lt;/a&gt; with the single link metric, with the dendrogram cut at height ε. Therefore, &lt;em&gt;minPts&lt;/em&gt; must be chosen at least 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hierarchical_clustering&quot;&gt;hierarchical clustering&lt;/a&gt; algorithm is more appropriate  for this application. However, as the outcome would be no different and we’d already done all the work to get DBSCAN working, we decided to stay with the DBSCAN implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-station-selection-algorithm&quot;&gt;Final station selection algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also other considerations beyond the clustering algorithm. We wanted as much representation for each country as possible. Even if a station is close to a station in another country, we wanted to include both of those stations (presuming they were otherwise good stations). We also didn’t want to keep stations that only have old data - we wanted our stations to be current. The whole selection algorithm is as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get all the stations listed in GHCNm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove from this list any station that does not have any records in the last 10 years or where we can’t calculate the temperature anomaly (60 years of total data)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If any country now has less than 5 stations, add the best stations for that country back into the list. (Better to have at least some representation for each country, even if it’s poor quality).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run DBSCAN at the country level, using an epsilon (i.e., ε or maximum distance between stations) of &lt;strong&gt;75km&lt;/strong&gt; and minPts of &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Germany is very dense with lots of good stations, reduce ε to 45km for Germany&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The USA is fairly dense with good stations, reduce ε to 70km for the USA&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove any duplicate stations that exist from other datasets (e.g., if the station exists in GHCNm and ACORN-SAT, remove that station from the GHCNm collection - we will preference ACORN-SAT)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we had done all that we had our stations from GHCNm that could then be integrated into the list of all stations and then into ClimateExplorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;criterion-3---data-resolution&quot;&gt;Criterion 3 - data resolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A downside of GHCNm is that it is monthly temperature records, not daily. We would prefer a daily record but have not found one that also fits with the other criteria. Another downside is that GHCNm is monthly mean, not maximum and minimums temperatures. Temperature gauge recording traditionally records the minimum and maximum. GHCNm has averaged the minimum and maximum and then averaged to a monthly value. This means some of the interesting graphs (e.g., number of days of frost) aren’t available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the data is monthly mean, we only need 12 values for the year, rather than the 730 values we have for stations with daily minimums and maximums. Therefore, storage space limitations disappear if we use GHCNm. When we include the adjusted (GHCNm call this QCF) and unadjusted (QCU) records, that’s still only 24 values a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;criterion-4---records-not-modelling&quot;&gt;Criterion 4 - records, not modelling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/products/land-based-station/global-historical-climatology-network-monthly&quot;&gt;GHCNm website&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Global Historical Climatology Network monthly (GHCNm) dataset provides monthly climate summaries from &lt;strong&gt;thousands of weather stations around the world&lt;/strong&gt;. (emphasis mine)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using GHCNm, we have only included data from really existing stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;criterion-5---precipitation&quot;&gt;Criterion 5 - precipitation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Precipitation data was available for each of the NOAA products. Given that we had all but settled on GHCNm, we needed to look at the GHCNm precipitation data. GHCNm Precipitation is currently a beta product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Global Historical Climatology Network (GHCN) Monthly Precipitation, Version 4 is a collection of worldwide monthly precipitation values offering significant enhancement over the previous version 2.  It contains more values both historically and for the most recent months.  Its methods for merging records and quality control have been modernized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The data set is updated typically in the first week of each month and available through the links below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precipitation data uses the same identifiers as GHCNm, thankfully. Surprisingly, and annoyingly, the access method and the format of the data between temperatures and precipitation are different. GHCNm temperature records are all in one big file, 1.5 million rows - about 160MB. We wrote a preprocessor to iterate through the file, pulling out each station and year of records - if a year didn’t have 12 months of recordings, the year was discarded. We had assumed GHCNm Precipitation would follow the same data structure. Unfortunately, each station is stored as a single file on their server, available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/data/ghcnm/v4beta/&quot;&gt;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/data/ghcnm/v4beta/&lt;/a&gt;. We needed to write a HTTP client that would connect to the server and download each file for the selected stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-extension&quot;&gt;Future extension&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using GHCNm, we are not able to display some of the interesting charts that rely on daily minimum and maximum temperatures and daily precipitation. A future extension could be to integrate GHCNd with GHCNm within ClimateExplorer. It is likely that the integration would be seamless as ClimateExplorer already has significant abstraction setup to support different datasets for Australia and New Zealand (e.g., ACORN-SAT vs standard BoM data). These daily data would only have unadjusted records (GHCNd only has raw values), but that would not be a problem as we could drop back to GHCNm when comparing adjusted vs raw values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another bonus is that the identifiers are the same for stations between GHCNd and GHCNm, though it would have been possible to identify stations by latitude and longitude anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only real concern in integrating GHCNd is whether we could support the increased storage space required. It would be a jump from 24 records per station, per year (12 for mean temperature and 12 for precipitation) to 1095 records per station, per year (365 for min temperature, 365 for max temperature and 365 for precipitation).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="datasets" /><summary type="html">In 2023 Climate Explorer had temperature records for Australia, New Zealand and the UK. We wanted to add temperature records from all around the world. Finding a dataset that fitted our requirements wasn’t easy. Below are the required criteria.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s up with temperature anomalies?</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/climate-science/2023/07/25/temperature-anomaly.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s up with temperature anomalies?" /><published>2023-07-25T18:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2023-07-25T18:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/climate-science/2023/07/25/temperature-anomaly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/climate-science/2023/07/25/temperature-anomaly.html">&lt;p&gt;An anomaly is anything that is &lt;em&gt;not normal&lt;/em&gt;. In science and mathematics, series of related numbers can be compared to discover anomalies within the series. To calculate a climate anomaly, we need to first &lt;em&gt;decide&lt;/em&gt; what is “normal”. Climate scientists have decided that any 30-year average of weather (i.e., average temperatures, rainfall or other phenomena) to be a sufficiently long enough period of time to use as a basis for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climatological_normal&quot;&gt;climatological normal&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/meta/2022/12/05/climatological-normals.html&quot;&gt;previous blog entry&lt;/a&gt; for more). Below we’ll discuss why and how climate anomalies are used in conjunction with a climate normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;temperature-anomaly&quot;&gt;Temperature anomaly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In climate science, a temperature anomaly has a specific meaning and method for calculation. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.noaa.gov/&quot;&gt;National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration&lt;/a&gt; (NOAA) explain it as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] the difference from an average, or &lt;em&gt;baseline&lt;/em&gt;, temperature. The baseline temperature is typically computed by averaging 30 or more years of temperature data. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/access/monitoring/dyk/anomalies-vs-temperature&quot;&gt;Anomalies vs. Temperature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anomalies can be used to determine how much a location has increased or decreased in temperature compared with the climate normal for that location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the average maximum temperature for Hobart (Tasmania, Australia), 1961-1990, is 17.2°C. If a yearly average max temperature is 18.5°C, the anomaly is 1.3°C. If a yearly average max temperature is 15.7°C, the anomaly is -1.5°C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparing-between-locations&quot;&gt;Comparing between locations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question we may want an answer to is: &lt;strong&gt;how do we compare temperatures from different locations to see if there is a general trend?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be great to &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; use anomalies. Why not simply average the raw temperature values (the absolute temperatures)? That would give results that are a lot easier to understand and relate to. If we wanted to compare Hobart with Darwin (Northern Territory, Australia) - two cities at the extremes of Australia - we can do that using absolute values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a table with Hobart’s and Darwin’s yearly average maximum temperature from 2011 until 2020. It also has the combined yearly average (third column) and the total averages (last row).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 1 (in °C)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Hobart&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Darwin&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Average&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;17.52&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;31.63&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;24.58&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.22&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.68&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.26&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.64&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.45&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;17.63&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.61&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;33.24&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.73&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.45&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.78&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.62&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2018&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.82&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.51&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2019&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.65&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.98&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.82&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;17.70&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;33.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18.08&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;32.68&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;25.39&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/access/monitoring/dyk/anomalies-vs-temperature&quot;&gt;web page about anomalies&lt;/a&gt;, NOAA’s explanation for their use in climate science does not lead with the best reason for using them. They discuss their use in regards to location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When calculating an average of absolute temperatures, things like station location or elevation will have an effect on the data (ex. higher elevations tend to be cooler than lower elevations and urban areas tend to be warmer than rural areas). However, when looking at anomalies, those factors are less critical. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncei.noaa.gov/access/monitoring/dyk/anomalies-vs-temperature&quot;&gt;Anomalies vs. Temperature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if temperature records were as good as the recent records for Hobart and Darwin, there would be no need to use anomalies. We have shown above that finding the average between wildly different locations is no big deal (it’s about 25°C for Darwin and Hobart).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NOAA’s second paragraph states the best reason to use anomalies; because climate data is irregular. The data is irregular because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stations start recording data at different times (some stations started recording more than one hundred years ago while others only started recording this year)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are often breaks in records, sometimes running for multiple consecutive years, sometimes with sporadic missing records&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stations stop recording permanently even though they have long runs of reliable readings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all of these conditions applying, it’s possible that Table 1 &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; look like Table 2, below. In Table 2, a fictitious example, Darwin’s station started recording in 2013 and shutdown at the end of 2019, while Hobart’s records are unavailable for the years 2015 and 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 2 (a fictitious variation of Table 1, in °C)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Hobart&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Darwin&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Average&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;17.52&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;17.52&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.68&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.26&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.64&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.45&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.61&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.61&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;33.24&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.73&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.45&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.78&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.62&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2018&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.82&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.82&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2019&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;18.65&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;32.98&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;25.82&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;17.70&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;17.70&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18.13&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;32.82&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24.68&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: we have applied a rule here that if a year is missing an average temperature we nevertheless average what is available. We could have a rule that if any year is missing, we refuse to average, and ignore the whole year. That would invalidate half of the results in this case, even though only one quarter of the initial data is missing. If we wanted to analyse many locations, we would even more frequently have to throw out whole years, or come up with another method for how many missing years are acceptable to still form a valid average. Once we group tens or hundreds of stations together, it’s very likely that some may experience issues in maintaining records on any given year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-anomalies-are-required&quot;&gt;Why anomalies are required&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s clear that the yearly averages for 2011, 2012, 2015, 2018 and 2020 in Table 2 are wildly inaccurate. There were no &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; fluctuations in temperature, but the averages suggest there are. It’s all due to missing data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of using absolute temperature averages, climate scientists are &lt;em&gt;forced&lt;/em&gt; to use anomaly averages because the historical record of temperatures are not standardised, long running, or reliable enough to use absolute temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a table where the same missing years of data exist as Table 2, but average anomalies are used instead of absolute temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 3 (a fictitious variation of Table 1, in anomalous °C)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Hobart&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Darwin&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Average anomaly&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.61&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.61&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.03&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.03&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.02&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.14&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.08&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.03&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.21&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.09&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.42&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.26&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.32&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.04&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.14&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2018&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.00&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2019&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.52&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.16&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0.34&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2020&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.43&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;-0.43&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18.13&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;32.82&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-0.07&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 25% of the records missing it would be difficult to have much confidence in the results no matter what analysis we attempt and yet Table 2 and Table 3 are completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you compare Table 3’s 2011 anomaly (-0.61°C) with Table 1’s anomaly (24.58°C - 25.39°C = -0.81°C), the difference is only 0.20°C. However, Table 2’s 2018 absolute temperature average (32.82°C) compared with the Table 1’s temperature average (25.51°C), shows a difference of 7.31°C!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that an analysis using anomalies is a much more reliable method when the temperature record contains missing data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we’re happy that this technique works well with some missing data (hopefully much less than 25%!), we can use it to aggregate not just Darwin and Hobart, but whole regions and ultimately, the world. &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/&quot;&gt;ClimateExplorer&lt;/a&gt; has recently applied these calculations for &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/regionalandglobal?csd=AverageOfAnomaliesInRegion,b13afcaf-cdbc-4267-9def-9629c8066321*TempMax*Adjusted*143983a0-240e-447f-8578-8daf2c0a246a,Mean,AutoAssigned,ByYear,Line,False,None,False,MovingAverage,20,Anomaly,,False,Identity,,True;AverageOfAnomaliesInRegion,e5eea4d6-5fd5-49ab-bf85-144a8921111e*Precipitation**143983a0-240e-447f-8578-8daf2c0a246a,Sum,AutoAssigned,ByYear,Line,False,None,False,MovingAverage,20,Anomaly,,False,Identity,,True&quot;&gt;all of Australia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference-period&quot;&gt;Reference period&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reference period is the last aspect of climate anomalies to discuss. The reference period is the time period that is selected to calculate the base average (the “climate normal”). The most important part of this process is to select a reference period that is representational for all of the locations in the collection. For instance, there is no point choosing 1901-1930 if most of the stations in the group weren’t operating during that period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/&quot;&gt;Australian Bureau of Meteorology (BoM)&lt;/a&gt; have selected 1961-1990 for their reference period (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/#tabs=ACORN%E2%80%90SAT&quot;&gt;ACORN-SAT&lt;/a&gt;). The UK Met Office Hadley Centre generally use the same reference period (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadcrut5/&quot;&gt;HadCRUT5&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.giss.nasa.gov/&quot;&gt;NASA GISS&lt;/a&gt; use &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.giss.nasa.gov/gistemp/faq/#q102&quot;&gt;1951-1980&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reference period selected will not change the shape of the resulting data and graphs, only the magnitudes of the anomalies. If the years 1991-2020 were selected, anomalies will rarely be above zero because that period is (currently) one of the hottest periods on record (i.e., most years on the temperature record will be colder than the period 1991-2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When compiling data for the Australian anomalies for ClimateExplorer, we used the same reference period as the BoM (1961-1990) while also requiring that each station have records for at least half of those years. When doing so we found that Burketown, Eucla, Learmonth, Morawa, Robe, Snowtown, and Victoria River Downs did not have enough records during that period. Those stations have been excluded from our analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;another-approach&quot;&gt;Another approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other ways we could cope with missing data and still use absolute temperatures. One of those methods is  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interpolation&quot;&gt;interpolation&lt;/a&gt;. The drawback of interpolation is that it’s more complicated to implement and - &lt;em&gt;more importantly&lt;/em&gt; - more difficult for people to understand. If we want to be able to convey how we can determine that global warming is happening, the simplest valid explanation is what we should lead with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;climate-sceptics-and-anomalies&quot;&gt;Climate sceptics and anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have explained why climate scientists present their large aggregation results (e.g., the global average temperature) as temperature anomalies. There is sufficient information to show that &lt;a href=&quot;https://wattsupwiththat.com/2023/03/12/new-wuwt-global-temperature-feature-anomaly-vs-real-world-temperature/&quot;&gt;sceptics’ complaints are unfounded&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless, what follows is a short discussion of some of their grievances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;weather-vs-climate&quot;&gt;Weather vs climate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] in the real-world, people don’t experience climate as yearly or monthly temperature anomalies, they experience &lt;em&gt;weather&lt;/em&gt; on a day to day basis, where one day may be abnormally warm, and another might be abnormally cold. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://wattsupwiththat.com/2023/03/12/new-wuwt-global-temperature-feature-anomaly-vs-real-world-temperature/&quot;&gt;WUWT&lt;/a&gt;, 2023)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statement from &lt;a href=&quot;https://wattsupwiththat.com&quot;&gt;Watts Up With That?&lt;/a&gt; (WUWT) isn’t false, it’s merely anti-scientific. Science is about trying to go beyond personal experience and common sense; it’s about analysis to justify hypothesis. Climate science has nothing to do with anyone’s experience of weather, it’s an analysis of long-term trends; for instance, trying to see if there is evidence of global warming from observed heating caused by greenhouse gases under controlled conditions (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eunice_Newton_Foote#%22Circumstances_Affecting_the_Heat_of_the_Sun&apos;s_Rays%22&quot;&gt;Eunice Foote&lt;/a&gt;, 1856). In this situation, a human’s sense of temperature is totally inadequate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;climate-conspiracy&quot;&gt;Climate conspiracy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is there nothing interesting in the two graphs in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wattsupwiththat.com/2023/03/12/new-wuwt-global-temperature-feature-anomaly-vs-real-world-temperature/&quot;&gt;WUWT&lt;/a&gt; article (“real” vs “anomaly”) - it’s the same graph with different scales on the y-axis - the article claims that &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.giss.nasa.gov/gistemp/&quot;&gt;NASA Goddard Institute of Space Studies&lt;/a&gt; has removed a method for converting from anomalies to absolute values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of course GISS &lt;em&gt;removed it&lt;/em&gt; from that page as seen today, because they don’t want people doing exactly what I’m doing now […] (WUWT, 2023)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not only has the information &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; been removed, it has been expanded to explain why the approach is fraught with errors, and why anomalies should be used rather than absolute temperatures when analysing global averages. (GISS FAQ was last updated Mar. 18, 2022. The &lt;em&gt;Watts Up With That?&lt;/em&gt; article was written Mar. 12, 2023 - there is no excuse for missing this information).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/assets/giss-absolute-temperature-14C.png&quot; alt=&quot;GISS FAQ that explains how conversions from anomaly to absolute temperature is done&quot; /&gt; From: &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.giss.nasa.gov/gistemp/faq/abs_temp.html&quot;&gt;The Elusive Absolute Surface Air Temperature&lt;/a&gt;, 2022&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;urban-heat-island&quot;&gt;Urban Heat Island&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WUWT also state that climate scientists don’t adjust for biases of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/green-infrastructure/reduce-urban-heat-island-effect&quot;&gt;Urban Heat Island (UHI)&lt;/a&gt;. The BoM explain that eight locations in their 112 ACORN-SAT sites are affected by this phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] four ACORN-SAT locations (Sydney, Melbourne, Adelaide and Hobart) were defined as urban in the initial classification, and four more (Laverton, Victoria; Richmond, New South Wales; Townsville and Rockhampton, Queensland) as urban-influenced […] These eight locations remain a part of the ACORN-SAT dataset, as they are important for monitoring changes in the climates in which many Australians live. However, &lt;strong&gt;they are not included in assessments of the warming trend across Australia or the calculation of national and State averages&lt;/strong&gt;. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/#tabs=FAQs&quot;&gt;ACORN-SAT FAQs&lt;/a&gt; - emphasis mine)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="climate-science" /><summary type="html">An anomaly is anything that is not normal. In science and mathematics, series of related numbers can be compared to discover anomalies within the series. To calculate a climate anomaly, we need to first decide what is “normal”. Climate scientists have decided that any 30-year average of weather (i.e., average temperatures, rainfall or other phenomena) to be a sufficiently long enough period of time to use as a basis for a climatological normal (see previous blog entry for more). Below we’ll discuss why and how climate anomalies are used in conjunction with a climate normal.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Climatological normal</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/climate-science/2022/12/05/climatological-normals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climatological normal" /><published>2022-12-05T18:40:00+11:00</published><updated>2022-12-05T18:40:00+11:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/climate-science/2022/12/05/climatological-normals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/climate-science/2022/12/05/climatological-normals.html">&lt;p&gt;While reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.noaa.gov/news/new-us-climate-normals-are-here-what-do-they-tell-us-about-climate-change&quot;&gt;a news article on US climate normals&lt;/a&gt;, I decided it might be better to use the most recent &lt;strong&gt;30 years&lt;/strong&gt; of temperature data to calculate the warming index, rather than &lt;strong&gt;20 years&lt;/strong&gt; of data. This change will align the warming index with the convention of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climatological_normal&quot;&gt;climatological normal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing the period that calculates the warming index will affect the heating score also because it’s calculated by finding the highest warming index across all locations and using that as the highest heating score. This results in a different distribution of scores over the map of Australia, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/location/darwin&quot;&gt;Darwin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/location/alice-springs&quot;&gt;Alice Springs&lt;/a&gt; coming out on the top of locations that have recorded the highest increases in temperature in Australia. They both record a 1.5°C increase in maximum temperature in the most recent 30 years, when compared with the first half of their dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/assets/australia-heating-scores-climate-normals.png&quot; alt=&quot;Australian heating scores using climate normals&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither approach (20 nor 30 years) is necessarily more correct than the other. It does not mean that Alice Springs and Darwin have warmed disproportionately more than other places around Australia. One of the biggest factors affecting the warming index is not to do with location at all, it’s about how far temperature records go back for that location. Alice Springs’ and Darwin’s records go back to the starting point for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/&quot;&gt;ACORN-SAT&lt;/a&gt; (1910); many other locations in ACORN-SAT started recording after 1910. For all more recent locations, their warming indexes are lower because there are fewer records to compare the recent history with. This is one of the factors that makes aggregating between locations such a challenge. Climate scientists have spent years collecting and aggregating records to remove any biases from the equipment, recording methods and durations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warming index and heating scores are not without utility, however. They’re a good guide for comparing coastal locations with inland and as a rough guide to compare the effect of global warming at different latitudes and elevations. One thing that is clear - whether it’s inland or coastal, rural or urban, Northern Australia or in the south: over the last 30 years maximum temperatures have trended up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="climate-science" /><summary type="html">While reading a news article on US climate normals, I decided it might be better to use the most recent 30 years of temperature data to calculate the warming index, rather than 20 years of data. This change will align the warming index with the convention of the climatological normal.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ACORN-SAT version 2.3</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2022/11/19/acorn-sat-2.3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ACORN-SAT version 2.3" /><published>2022-11-19T19:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2022-11-19T19:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2022/11/19/acorn-sat-2.3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/datasets/2022/11/19/acorn-sat-2.3.html">&lt;p&gt;ACORN-SAT version 2.3 was release 2022-11-18. Version 2.3 has temperatures records from 1910 up until the end of 2021, for the 112 locations around Australia included in ACORN-SAT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map below (from &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/&quot;&gt;ClimateExplorer&lt;/a&gt;) shows heating scores calculated from version 2.3 of ACORN-SAT. Canberra is no longer the only location that has a heating score of 9. There are now 5 sites that share that score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heating score is a relative metric; it’s the result of comparing all warming indexes with all others in the dataset. The other sites (&lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/location/alice-springs&quot;&gt;Alice Springs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/location/cunderdin&quot;&gt;Cunderdin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/location/marree&quot;&gt;Marree&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/location/snowtown&quot;&gt;Snowtown&lt;/a&gt;) were boosted to a 9 because they had warmer than average temperatures in 2021. Canberra had its first cooler than average temperature since 1996 (25 years). That reduced Canberra’s warming index from 1.8°C to 1.7°C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/assets/australia-heating-scores-acorn-sat-2.3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Australian heating scores from ACORN-SAT 2.3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/&quot;&gt;Bureau of Meteorology&lt;/a&gt; released a statement about version 2.3 on their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/&quot;&gt;ACORN-SAT website&lt;/a&gt;, reproduced below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h3 id=&quot;new-and-reassessed-adjustments-as-part-of-acorn-sat-version-23&quot;&gt;New and reassessed adjustments as part of ACORN-SAT version 2.3&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;ACORN-SAT 2.3 includes new or reassessed adjustments at 16 of the 112 ACORN-SAT locations. Previously applied adjustments at 7 locations were removed after being found to be no longer significant with the inclusion of additional data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Analysis has shown the changed adjustments in ACORN-SAT 2.3 have had a negligible impact on estimated long-term warming trend in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Full details of all adjustments, including the time periods and reference periods used, are available in the station catalogue. The Bureau’s ACORN-SAT dataset and methods have been thoroughly peer-reviewed and found to be world-leading. Further information on the dataset and the reasons for adjustments can be found in the ACORN-SAT &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/#tabs=FAQs&quot;&gt;FAQ section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="datasets" /><summary type="html">ACORN-SAT version 2.3 was release 2022-11-18. Version 2.3 has temperatures records from 1910 up until the end of 2021, for the 112 locations around Australia included in ACORN-SAT.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chart options information</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/site-info/2022/11/19/chart-options-information.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chart options information" /><published>2022-11-19T06:16:00+11:00</published><updated>2022-11-19T06:16:00+11:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/site-info/2022/11/19/chart-options-information</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/site-info/2022/11/19/chart-options-information.html">&lt;p&gt;When using &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net&quot;&gt;ClimateExplorer&lt;/a&gt;, you may notice that below the chart there is a cluster of buttons that allow you to customise the data and the chart. This post explains what they are and how to use them. There is a general help (chart options) and detailed information on two of the more complicated areas. The sections are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chart options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Year filtering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aggregation options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chart-options-information&quot;&gt;Chart options information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/assets/chart-options.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chart options information&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Year filtering: allows you to change the start and end years for the chart. For example, if you want to see the change in temperature for the 20th century, you could set the end year to 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clear filter: the clear filter button is only displayed when there is a start or end year filter applied to the chart. Clicking this button will reset the chart back to the default filter and remove the range slider (if it has been turned on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grouping&lt;/strong&gt;: the grouping option allows you to look at the data from another point of view. The default view is “Yearly”; i.e., each point on the graph represents a single year in the series. To represent daily data at the yearly level, ClimateExplorer applies rules and aggregations to average (or sum) the data together. If you select “Year + Month” the data will be re-processed, starting with the daily data for the particular year, to present twelve points on the chart per year. This view works best in combination with the range slider. If you select “Month”, the data will be sliced, again starting with the lowest level of the data (usually daily), into only twelve points, one point for every month of the year. The value for each point will be an average (or sum) of the data across all years. This will give you a climatic view of the data for the location, it will not be as useful for viewing the change in the climate over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download data&lt;/strong&gt;: the download data button allows you to download, as a csv file, the data for the chart you are currently looking at. The button is context sensitive; it’ll download data that applies to the current view. For example, if you are looking at the data as a “Year + Month” grouping, you will get twelve records for each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aggregation options&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;advanced&lt;/em&gt; feature): the aggregation options allow you to change the underlying grouping parameters for the chart. The default values will group the daily data into 14 day (i.e., fortnightly) sub-bins. If each of those sub-bins has records for 70% of those days (i.e., 10 days of the 14 days will need to have records) then the whole year is considered valid. This means that you can still have substantial data loss for the year (e.g., the meteorologist was unwilling to come in on weekends to record the min and max temperatures)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add data set&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;advanced&lt;/em&gt; feature): the suggested charts at the bottom of the screen provide the user with a number of predefined and recommended charts that can be viewed within ClimateExplorer. Other datasets can be added in an ad-hoc manner with the “Add data set” button. The list on the “Add data set” dialog contains data for your current location, such as solar radiation and the diurnal range for temperature. The list also contains reference data sets that can be added, such as CO₂, ENSO indexes and data from the cryosphere (the cryosphere comprises the parts of the planet that are frozen most of the year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;year-filtering-information&quot;&gt;Year filtering information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/assets/year-filtering.png&quot; alt=&quot;Year filtering information&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dialog allows you to change the start and end years for the chart. For example, if you want to see the change in temperature/rainfall for the 20th century, you could set the end year to 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range slider&lt;/strong&gt;: if you want to browse the start/end years of the chart, the range slider may be helpful. It allows you to the change the range of years on the chart, using a slider control. The range slider supports increasing and decreasing the start and end year individually. By moving the slider within the extents, it will change both start and end years at the same time. For example, you could filter to only 30 years of data, between 1910 and 1940, then move the slider to another set of 30 years, between 1940 and 1970.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dynamically set the start year of the chart to be the most recent start year across all the datasets on the chart&lt;/strong&gt;: when this is checked, the start year for the chart will be the last start year found across the datasets. For example, Canberra’s temperature records start in 1914. Canberra’s rainfall records start in 1924. With the option checked, the chart will start in 1924 because that’s the latest start year. The start year for the chart will dynamically adjust to whatever datasets are selected for viewing. This option is checked by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aggregation-options-information&quot;&gt;Aggregation options information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/assets/aggregation-options.png&quot; alt=&quot;Aggregation options information&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aggregation options are advanced features that allows you to change the underlying aggregation process. To calculate a single aggregated value for data for a year, from daily or monthly series, data is bundled together. If each bundle of data does not have enough records, the bundle is rejected as being unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, the bundles are groups of 14 days (fortnights) and each bundle requires 70% (10 days of the 14) of the records to be present for the year to be considered reliable enough for an average mean to be calculated. This means that a number of records can be missing for the year, so long as not too many consecutive days are missing. As temperature (and other climate data) follows cyclic patterns, missing data from a consecutive block is considered to be more untrustworthy than sporadic data missing throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some presets (specifically, the cryosphere reference data – sea ice extent and melt) have a lower threshold applied to them because the data has been curated and considered to be trustworthy enough that more of it can be missing while still not corrupting the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you make changes to these settings and apply them, your settings will take precedence and override any preset specific settings. You can clear this by clicking “Clear override” which would have appeared after you applied your changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day grouping&lt;/strong&gt;: select groups from weekly, fortnightly, monthly, and half-yearly, amongst other options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threshold required to form a valid group (% percentage)&lt;/strong&gt;: this is a percentage of how many records is considered sufficient to form a valid bundle of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apply&lt;/strong&gt;: save your changes and apply them to the chart. These settings will persist as you change locations and datasets within the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear override&lt;/strong&gt;: this will reset the settings back to their default (14 days at 70% threshold). Only appears after applying your settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="site-info" /><summary type="html">When using ClimateExplorer, you may notice that below the chart there is a cluster of buttons that allow you to customise the data and the chart. This post explains what they are and how to use them. There is a general help (chart options) and detailed information on two of the more complicated areas. The sections are:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Location summary information</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/site-info/2022/11/11/location-summary-information.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Location summary information" /><published>2022-11-11T06:39:00+11:00</published><updated>2022-11-11T06:39:00+11:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/site-info/2022/11/11/location-summary-information</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/site-info/2022/11/11/location-summary-information.html">&lt;p&gt;When you use ClimateExplorer, you may see info boxes that explain a few of the climate-related concepts presented in the web application. In the location summary area, they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Warming index&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heating score&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Climate stripe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought it might be a good idea to present the text on the blog, as a summary of some of the concepts. Below is what you may see as pop-up text if you click on the corresponding area in the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/blog/assets/Canberra-location-info.png&quot; alt=&quot;Canberra-location-info&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warming-index&quot;&gt;Warming index&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warming index is the temperature difference between the average of the last 20 years of maximum temperatures compared with the average of the first half (50 years) of the dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canberra, between the years 2001-2020, had an average max temp of &lt;strong&gt;21.06°C&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canberra, between the years 1914-1970, had an average max temp of &lt;strong&gt;19.29°C&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference is &lt;strong&gt;+1.8°C&lt;/strong&gt; (after rounding to 1 decimal place).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the long-term, with no external influences, we’d expect the warming index to trend towards zero. A non-zero warming index may indicate an effect of climate change. A positive warming index may indicate global warming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;heating-score&quot;&gt;Heating score&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heating score is a number typically between 0 and 9. It is derived from comparing all warming indexes across the locations in the dataset. The highest warming index is used to standardise the values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calculate the heating score:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For warming indexes that are greater than zero, divide the warming index by the maximum warming index in the set, multiple by 9 and round to zero decimal places.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For warming indexes that are less than zero, the only operation done is to round the number to zero demical places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The score may be higher if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The location is inland. The ocean is warming more slowly compared with the land. Coastal locations are therefore likely to have warmed less than inland locations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The station(s) has been operating for a long time. The effect of global warming is more obvious with a large dataset as temperatures in the past were cooler.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;climate-stripe&quot;&gt;Climate stripe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warming_stripes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Climate stripes&lt;/a&gt; are a simplified bar chart of average temperatures, ordered by year, from the earliest year in the record until the most recent. Each coloured stripe represents a single year of temperature data. A blue stripe is a year where the temperature is below the average of the whole series. A red stripe represents an above average temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate stripe colours are calculated by the following algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Calculate the average temperature for the whole series (e.g., Canberra 1914-2020 mean is 19.8°C)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For each year in the series, subtract the average temperature for the &lt;strong&gt;year&lt;/strong&gt; from the average for the &lt;strong&gt;series&lt;/strong&gt;. Note:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This value in step 2 is often called the temperature anomaly&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If the anomaly is above 0°C, we consider it a warmer than average year&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If the anomaly is below 0°C, we consider it a colder than average year&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Find the coldest anomaly (e.g., Canberra’s is -2°C) and assign it the strongest colour of blue&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Find the warmest anomaly (e.g., Canberra’s is 2.9°C) and assign it the strongest colour of red&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All anomalies between the extremes are lighter shades of blue or red&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate Explorer’s stripe is interactive. Hover over any year in the series then click. The chart will update with a monthly view of the selected year.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="site-info" /><summary type="html">When you use ClimateExplorer, you may see info boxes that explain a few of the climate-related concepts presented in the web application. In the location summary area, they are:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to the Climate Explorer blog</title><link href="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/meta/2022/11/04/welcome-to-climate-explorer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to the Climate Explorer blog" /><published>2022-11-04T14:40:17+11:00</published><updated>2022-11-04T14:40:17+11:00</updated><id>https://climateexplorer.net/blog/meta/2022/11/04/welcome-to-climate-explorer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://climateexplorer.net/blog/meta/2022/11/04/welcome-to-climate-explorer.html">&lt;p&gt;Hey, welcome to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/&quot;&gt;Climate Explorer&lt;/a&gt; blog! We plan to use this blog to keep you up to date as we add features &amp;amp; data sets to &lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/&quot;&gt;Climate Explorer&lt;/a&gt;, as well as linking to further reading on the source data sets and climate concepts related to the site. We may also talk a little about how the site is implemented behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-climate-explorer&quot;&gt;What is Climate Explorer?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://climateexplorer.net/&quot;&gt;Climate Explorer&lt;/a&gt; was created to help people understand climate change. It’s focussed on trying to provide a simple and approachable interface for people to explore. The types of data include temperature, rainfall and large-scale weather patterns like ENSO (El Niño/La Niña) and the Indian Ocean Dipole (IOD). So far, we’ve focussed on Australia and New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-is-the-website-for&quot;&gt;Who is the website for?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: right;width: 10rem;&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/HotTalkColdScience.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover of boom Hot Talk, Cold Science&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website was created with climate sceptics in mind. It was created after one of the programmers started a review of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/1610224.Hot_Talk_Cold_Science&quot;&gt;Hot Talk, Cold Science: Global Warming’s Unfinished Debate&lt;/a&gt;. We intend to contribute the review of this book, over multiple parts, on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind Climate Explorer was to provide an accessible website that allows users to explore the temperature data provided by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/&quot;&gt;Bureau of Meteorology&lt;/a&gt; (BoM). The initial focus was to permit the user to compare the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/#tabs=Methods&quot;&gt;adjusted temperature records&lt;/a&gt; with the unadjusted records. The BoM do a good job of explaining why they adjust the records over the long-term. Their reasoning is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;a shift in the location of the station (for example, from a post office to an airport);&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;a change in the environment around the station (for example a tree grows, a structure is built, a lawn is irrigated); or&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;a change in measurement method (for example, from a manual instrument to a recording electronic instrument).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sceptical response to the BoM may be: “you haven’t provided all of the evidence, so how are we supposed to make up our minds?” Climate Explorer allows the user to look at any location used in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/data/acorn-sat/&quot;&gt;ACORN-SAT&lt;/a&gt; and compare the adjusted with the unadjusted records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;contact-us&quot;&gt;Contact us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any feedback, suggestions or questions, feel free to let us know at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:climateexplorerteam@gmail.com&quot;&gt;climateexplorerteam@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="meta" /><summary type="html">Hey, welcome to the Climate Explorer blog! We plan to use this blog to keep you up to date as we add features &amp;amp; data sets to Climate Explorer, as well as linking to further reading on the source data sets and climate concepts related to the site. We may also talk a little about how the site is implemented behind the scenes.</summary></entry></feed>